[Music]
first there was sugar and high fructose
corn syrup the original industrial
sweeteners they were cheap but had lots
of empty calories and contributed to
diseases such as obesity type 2 diabetes
cavities and metabolic syndrome
so then came the second generation
sweeteners the artificial sweeteners the
colored pastel packets nutrasweet
splenda sweet and love
practically zero calories but adverse
effects have been described cautions
have been raised for example artificial
sweeteners were found to induce glucose
intolerance by altering the gut
microbiome thereby producing the
counter-intuitive effect of inducing
metabolic derangements
they also
taste kind of funny
enter the third generation sweeteners
sugar alcohol such as sorbitol xylitol
and erythritol
low calorie sweeteners however their
laxative effects can create difficulties
which brings us to
rare sugars like allulose which are
natural sweeteners with low or zero
calories and a sugar-like taste
for those of you who haven't heard of
allulose it's been through a bit of
rebranding just like rapeseed oil
morphed into canola
forcing municipalities to
update their town slogans
aguilos used to be called psychos a
sugar you may not want to eat in the
shower the name psychos is derived from
the antibiotic from which it was
isolated that's a strange origin story
for a sweetener
in the frontiers of bioengineering and
biotechnology emphasis is placed on the
fact that allulose is a real and natural
sugar rather than artificial but
ironically if you look at the reference
they cite it talks about how allulose is
made via functionalized polyhydroxy
alkynoate nanobeads decorated with
d-taggitos 3 epimerase dte produced in
recombinant endotoxin-free branded
bacteria
and now technically augulos is a natural
sugar a so-called rare sugar which has
been defined by the international
society of rare sugars as sugars that
are present in limited quantities in
nature but recent technological advances
such as enzymatic engineering using
genetically modified microorganisms now
allow manufacturers to produce otherwise
rare sugars like allulose in substantial
quantities
but small amounts have pre-existed in
the food supply so the fda granted it
generally recognized as safe status but
it's spin like really small amounts like
a few dozen milligrams or a quarter of a
quarter of a quarter of a teaspoon
see algalos is generated when fructose
is heated that's why this poor guy kept
breaking out in hives eating such a
strange variety of foods because he
happened to be allergic to allulose and
nagulos is created incidentally in the
process by which high fructose corn
syrup is made so
basing the safety value loss on the fact
that it's already been present in the
food supply isn't very convincing
you don't know if it's safe until you
put it to the test
unlike table sugar alulos is safe for
the teeth isn't apparently metabolized
by cavity causing bacteria to make acid
and
build up plaque
it doesn't raise blood sugars even in
diabetics it can be labeled as having
zero calories though technically it may
have like one and a half calories per
teaspoon similar to what you see with
erythritol
also like erythritol it's only about 70
percent as sweet as table sugar but has
almost the same taste performance and
texture as regular sugar are there any
toxicities
allelos is considered a relatively
non-toxic sugar
what does that mean
well in pets we know a sweetener called
xylitol can be extremely dangerous in
dogs as little as a half teaspoon and a
30 pound dog can be life threatening
whereas a similar dose of value loss
apparently wouldn't be a problem though
like over a half cup at a time could
make them sick
this was a single dose study though the
long-term safety valueless was tested
over a period of a few months and didn't
seem to cause any harmful effects at a
dose of about one and a half teaspoons a
day for healthy 30 pound dogs in fact
their cholesterol actually went down
leading the investigators to suggest
clinical studies to see if it's
something vets should start prescribing
for overweight pooches
what about in people
when the dose of allulose was gradually
increased to identify the maximum single
dose for occasional ingestion no cases
of severe gastrointestinal symptoms were
noted until a dose of 0.4 grams per
kilogram of body weight was reached
which could be about 7 teaspoons with
severe symptoms of diarrhea noted once
you get up around nine teaspoons and you
say who could eat that much sugar at a
time anyway
a single can of coke has ten teaspoons
and a bottle of mountain dew has nearly
twice that so alose is clearly not
suitable as a standalone sweetener for
sugary beverages
in terms of the daily upper limit given
in smaller doses throughout the day
once you get around 17 teaspoons a day
depending on your weight people start
getting severe nausea abdominal pain
headache diarrhea so people should
probably stay under single doses of
about 7 teaspoons and not exceed around
15 for the whole day
the average american may be getting 17
teaspoons of added sugar a day so it's
certainly not something the food
industry can completely switch over to
in this way allelosa was close to
xylitol in terms of maximal single dose
whereas the average weight man in the
u.s could get away with 14 teaspoons of
erythritol at a time and the average
woman 15 teaspoons
still not enough to sweeten a bottle of
coke but offers a little more leeway for
sweetening tea or sprinkling on a
grapefruit or something
aguilos is claimed to provide health
benefits though compared to erythritol
fourth generation sweeteners like alloss
are said to have an advantage additional
functions
we'll find out if that's true
next
[Music]
you